<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Expedients for publique peace. Shewing the necessity of a national union and the way to it in this time of danger.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 31 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84298</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3887</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1021_8</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208386</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867341</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867341</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119648</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84298)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119648)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 151:E1021[8])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Expedients for publique peace. Shewing the necessity of a national union and the way to it in this time of danger.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed, in the year, 1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "April. 20".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119648:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>EXPEDIENTS FOR Publique Peace.</p>
            <p>Shewing the <hi>Neceſsity</hi> of a <hi>NATIONAL <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NION</hi> And the way to it in this time of Danger.</p>
            <q>
               <l>— En, que diſcordia Cives</l>
               <l>Perduxit miſeros.—</l>
            </q>
            <p>Printed, In the Year, 1660.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:119648:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:119648:2"/>
            <head>EXPEDIENTS FOR Publique Peace.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough the Providence of God hath won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully begun our conduct towards <hi>Settlement,</hi> not through a <hi>Red-ſea</hi> of <hi>bloud,</hi> (which both our ſins deſerved, and our late condition threatned) but a Cryſtal ſtream of calme waters; and though his goodneſs hath, beyond our hopes, appeared in <hi>confounding</hi> even <hi>confuſion</hi> it ſelf, in diſſipating the proudeſt Faction that ever was, ſince the fall of Angels, and building of <hi>Babel.</hi> And (to ſpeak their own language) in bearing witneſs againſt them, not by the Event of Battel (the Appeal of <hi>Turks</hi> and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119648:3"/>
               <hi>Pirates</hi>) but by a mighty influence upon our <hi>ſpirits,</hi> firſt opening our eyes, in ſome meaſure, to ſee the things that belong to our Peace, and then moving our hearts to purſue, as <hi>mediums</hi> thereunto, whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and ſound Principles; yet our reſtleſs ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies are no whit diſcouraged, but rather their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice increaſes, in meaſure, as their hopes diminiſh. Had they Charity, Modeſty, Prudence, or common ſenſe, which (one would think) the univerſal tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs expreſt, upon the accompt of very doubtful hopes, and general ſuffrage of ſuch, as ſpeak with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out intereſt or deſign, might prompt unto them, it would either daunt their Preſumption, or, at leaſt, oblige them, ſeriouſly to conſider, Whether any thing in this tranſitory world, collateral to our eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, and by experience, not neceſſary to our preſent happineſs, is worth the purchaſing with ſo much hazard to themſelves, and ruine to others; but it ſeems, that having paſſed the <hi>Rubicon</hi> of honeſty and diſcretion, they reſolve either to periſh them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, or ſack <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, perceiving, they can do no good their own way, they will do what miſchief they are able, being thereto incited, by the two common enemies, <hi>(viz.)</hi> the Devil and the Jeſuite, They ſee it is too vain for them to contend for the major Vote in Parliament, ſince they can ſcarce prevail in any, even the leaſt Corporation; For the ſober and moderate Party, excluding both extremes, (whether Fanatique Common-wealths-men, or Royal Hectors) doth now carry with it the ſenſe of the people. Wherefore like Good Pilots, (if
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119648:3"/>free booters may deſerve that ſtile) they have lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to tack about to the wind, to refine their groſs pretences, and appear no more in their own diabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall ſhape, but diſguiſed habit of true <hi>Parliamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teers</hi> as if they had never prevaricated from their principles in the firſt Warre.</p>
            <p>They find, (no queſtion) their own weakneſſe, in not having any colour of reaſon, or ſhadow of <hi>Authority,</hi> No, not ſo much, as the <hi>Rump</hi> of a <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> to countenance their <hi>Uſurpations,</hi> The le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall and ſolemn diſſolution of that, which could only give them a <hi>baſis</hi> (though a very falſe and as they made, it rotten one,) having diſappointed all their <hi>projects</hi> by turning the ſtream into the channel of free, and <hi>triennial elections;</hi> ſo as, now, they muſt begin the <hi>World</hi> anew. And are forced like broken <hi>Citizens</hi> in <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> to ſet up an <hi>Alehouſe,</hi> or <hi>Chandlers ſhop</hi> in the ſuburbs to ſeek out ſome new probability of ſhifting, and ſubſiſting.</p>
            <p>The eſcape of <hi>Lambert</hi> wil not now avail them, He is in il condition to <hi>head</hi> a <hi>Faction</hi> that dares not ſee a <hi>Conſtable</hi> on <hi>Engliſh ground;</hi> The caſe is fairly altered, <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>poſſeſsion,</hi> the <hi>City, Country</hi> and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter part of the <hi>Army</hi> now ſtand right, <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> are good ſeconds, our Government being in the hands of a <hi>Vigilant Counſell,</hi> our Forces both by <hi>Land</hi> and <hi>Sea</hi> under the Command of an invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible <hi>Captain,</hi> The Nation concerned not only for its <hi>Liberty</hi> but its <hi>being;</hi> We are therefore I truſt reaſonably ſafe, from their batteries and aſſaults, but let us not think our ſelves ſecure from their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermining. A <hi>Rogue</hi> by profeſſion ought alwaies
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119648:4"/>to be ſuſpected, For, if he cannot <hi>command</hi> your Purſe, he will do the beſt he can to <hi>pick</hi> it.</p>
            <p>The <hi>moderate Presbyterian,</hi> and <hi>ſober Royall</hi> Principle do manifeſtly divide almoſt the whole Nation between them: This hath the greater part of the <hi>Nobility</hi> and <hi>Gentry,</hi> that the <hi>Principal Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porations:</hi> The ſincere uniting, and incorporating of theſe two Parties, I look upon as a matter of ſuch importance, that alone, it ſeeures and diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pates all our fears, and renders us invincible not only to the <hi>Phanaticks,</hi> but probably (with Gods bleſſing) to any Invader. On the other ſide, their <hi>mutual diſcord</hi> (nay though it were but <hi>Jealouſie</hi>) will be a <hi>brack,</hi> (and perhaps the only <hi>brack</hi>) in our Foundation: This indeed, may once more daſh us in pieces; however, it will certainly diſpoſe us to all thoſe Dangers and Viciſſitudes, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly attend thoſe Governments, where the <hi>Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> are mighty, and equally poyſed; the billows ſwelling ſo high, that ſcarce any <hi>Pilot</hi> can ſteer the <hi>Veſſel</hi> to its <hi>Port,</hi> or come ſafely to an <hi>Anchor:</hi> In fine, this is like to give <hi>courage</hi> and <hi>opportunity</hi> to the <hi>Phanaticks;</hi> who, though I am confident, they can never ſettle themſelves, may nevertheleſs long diſquiet, and greatly torment us.</p>
            <p>Of this our Enemies (a ſubtle Generation) cannot but be highly ſenſible, it being ſo obvious to every capacity; And therefore their whole bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe now is, as we Proverbially ſpeak, <hi>to drive that nail that will goe:</hi> Herein conſiſts the ſum of all our fears, and their hopes; hitherto all their <hi>Jeſuited Councels</hi> tend: And they preſume they
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119648:4"/>ſhall neither want excellent Tools to work with, nor fitting matter to work upon: the Fuel, they ſuppoſe is not like <hi>Greenwood,</hi> which will not kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle to any purpoſe, without long and induſtrious blowing the Coals; but rather like <hi>Charcoal,</hi> which being already half burned, is obnoxious almoſt to every ſpark: The memory of things paſt revived, and aggravated, the cenſure of things preſent, and evil preſage of future, is the work they have to do. Their Inſtruments are the <hi>Extravagants</hi> on both ſides, and none more then <hi>Cavaliers,</hi> whom they cunningly Cajole, by telling them, how much they preferre <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> before <hi>Preſbytery;</hi> how much they eſteem them a Nobler Enemy, and had rather (if one they muſt chooſe) receive Lawes from them; that ſtately <hi>Elms</hi> are better then ſtinking <hi>Elders;</hi> that <hi>Charles Stuart</hi> (as they call him) is a <hi>goodly Cedar</hi> in reſpect of our late <hi>Shrubs:</hi> With many other the like Inſinuations, tending only to heighten the <hi>pretences</hi> of that Party, (naturally apt to be too vain) and ſo to fatten them for the ſlaughter: To the <hi>Rigid Presbyterians,</hi> they ſpeak in a different ſtrain, (for the Saints, I muſt tell you, have learned of their great Maſter, to appear in divers ſhapes, like a fair Lady to Gallants, and a Capuchin to Bigotts,) I ſhall not here repeat their Malicious ſurmiſes and ſuggeſtions: Their late <hi>Venemous Newes</hi> from <hi>Bruxelles,</hi> The <hi>Alarm to the Army, Plain Engliſh,</hi> and other Pamphlets of the ſame tincture, will ſoon teach you their <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage,</hi> if you be not too <hi>honeſt</hi> to learn it.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:119648:5"/>
            <p>The great Concernments, and indefatigable En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours of this (now, God be thanked) <hi>Common Enemy,</hi> to <hi>ſow the ſeeds of Diſcord amongſt Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,</hi> and thereby make way for our <hi>Ruine</hi> and their own <hi>Ends,</hi> (otherwiſe impoſſible to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed) ſhould certainly convince us, that we ought, at leaſt wiſe not our ſelves, to ſerve and further their Deſigns, but rather to trace the <hi>Serpent</hi> in his crooked motions, to countermine him in his under-ground workings; and at once <hi>wiſely</hi> and <hi>generouſly</hi> reſolve (however we may differ in Trifles and Circumſtances, (which vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, doubtleſs, amongſt men of <hi>Charity</hi> and <hi>Temper</hi> muſt needs either be eaſily reconciled, or innocently continued,) yet) alwayes to unite cloſely in the Main, that our ſtrife prove but an <hi>Emulation,</hi> which of us for the future ſhall be the better <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh-men, (viz.)</hi> more modeſt in our <hi>Pretences,</hi> moderate in our <hi>Aſſertions,</hi> peaceable in our <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultations,</hi> charitable in our <hi>Cenſures,</hi> &amp; fervent only in <hi>reall Duties.</hi> To the furtherance of which bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Union, or, (as it may well be ſtyled) <hi>benigne Conſtellation,</hi> there are many motives, (I think) as conſiderable, as the End propounded, <hi>(viz.)</hi> our <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Happineſſe</hi> can render them.</p>
            <p>The example of your Adverſaries ſummons you to doe that for <hi>prudence</hi> and <hi>ſelf-preſervation,</hi> which they do for <hi>Malice</hi> and <hi>Faction:</hi> They who have ſcarce any Doctrines wherein they agree, otherwiſe then as <hi>Foxes tayls,</hi> to burn our Corn, little Sobriety or Temper, but what their crafty Nature, ſhrewd Maxims, and Wordly experience
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119648:5"/>gives them, no means of Reconciliation, in caſe of diſagreement, every one being his own Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, his own Church, (as the name of <hi>Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency</hi> it ſelf imports,) They who could never com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with any <hi>Eſtabliſhment,</hi> but the very name of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fends them; and when both the Peoples neceſſities, and their own, called aloud for ſomewhat of <hi>Settle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> choſe rather to rot and periſh, then to have their Ulcers any way dreſſed; yet now all theſe conſent, or rather combine, (and that very unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly) againſt our <hi>Peace.</hi> Sir <hi>Henry Vane,</hi> and Sir <hi>Arthur Hazlerigge, Lambert</hi> and <hi>Scott, Rump,</hi> and <hi>Committee of ſafety,</hi> all on the ſuddain united in their hopes and endeavours, to ruine their <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey:</hi> Nay, moſt obſervable it is, that in the midſt of their greateſt <hi>Diſsentions,</hi> (and <hi>Chaos</hi> it ſelf (I think) had not greater) they were ſo tender of deſtroying, or but branding each other, (know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, it ſeems, their Diſeaſe to be ſuch, that Bleeding or Scarrifying would prove mortall to them) as if they had only played a Match at Foot-ball or Cud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells for the Dominion. Our Government was frequently altered without a broken Pate, or bloudy Noſe: And thoſe who ſhould have been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned as <hi>Notorious Uſurpers,</hi> and <hi>Traytors,</hi> ſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped either under the notion of <hi>diſſenting Brethren,</hi> or with the ſoft cenſure of <hi>Backſliders;</hi> ſo ſenſible they were of the neceſſity to connive at each others guilt: What a happineſſe and ſecurity were it to the Nation, if Perſons, in their <hi>Fundamentals</hi> ſound and Orthodox, in their <hi>Profeſsions</hi> I hope, ſincere, could arrive but at half ſo much Candour
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119648:6"/>and Prudence, or that the men of this world were not much wiſer in their generation, then Children of light.</p>
            <p>Matter of common principle directs and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwades you, as ſober Aſſertors of the ſame Law, and Religion, to ſtand and fall together. It is the obſervation of your enemies (and a very true one) that you differ only <hi>gradu,</hi> not <hi>rê,</hi> you both ſubſcribe, That the Majeſty of Princes is inviolable, their Rights Divine, their Perſons Sacred; The neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of outward Miſſion, Decency, and Uniformity (if it may be) in Gods ſervice: The Rights of the Miniſtery to their Tithes, by known Law and Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, grounded upon ancient Piety and great Mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, are on both ſides equally confeſt and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained. Theſe are the ſubſtance, me-thinks your Contentions about meer Rights and Circumſtances ſhould neither be great, nor long, eſpecially, being ſo deſtructive to mutual happineſs; me-thinks, mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters might be compounded, by friendly Conference or Reference, both ſides receding and meeting each other in the way to Peace, for ſuch is the Rule of fair arbitrations; Me-thinks you ſhould reflect, how little either of you hath advanced towards his deſired ends, by long and ruinous Diſcord; you ſhould ſee, and foreſee, how little ground hath or will probably be gained, by pertinacy or animoſity; You ſhould examine, Whether it be not better now to ſecure your Conſciences, Lives, and Laws, by a ſeaſonable compliance with each other in matters not Eſſential, then ſeven, perhaps twenty years hence, after much innocent bloud vainly ſpilt, your
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119648:6"/>Eſtares diminiſhed, your Countrey waſted, perhaps be ſubdued, and forced to buckle in all your Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſions, but at beſt, to purchaſe a moſt Un-chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an triumph, and a dear repentance even in Victory. You <hi>Cavaliers</hi> ſhould remember, That could you oppreſs or deſtroy the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> (which you muſt never hope to effect) you would but weaken your own hands, pluck down your beſt fences, and even by your Conqueſt expoſe your ſelves, at leaſt your Poſterity, to meer Arbitrary Power, and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Law; a condition, which few of you, I truſt, would impoſe, none of you, I am ſure, would em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace. You <hi>Presbyterians</hi> ſhould conſider, That could you extirpate the <hi>Royall party</hi> (which is yet more impoſſible) you would let in the Phanaticks as a Torrent, to whom you lie very open and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious, <hi>(viz.)</hi> to be beaten with all your own weapons, and confuted with the ſame Arguments (both in Civils and Spirituals) which your ſelves invented againſt the <hi>Royalliſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Common Exigence, &amp; Charity to your Countrey conjures you, to redreſs, if poſſible, her Grievances, eaſe her Burthens and Oppreſſions, redeem her Captivity, regulate her Confuſions in Church and State, reſtore her loſt Trade, and in ſome meaſure, relieve an incredible number of deſerving Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and Noble Famelies, now periſhing, of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Citizens, now dayly breaking; of hopefull Scholars, now deſparing of a bare livelihood. This cannot poſſibly be effected by the continuance of our Diſtractions, ſince Reaſon, and Experience in abundance may teach us, That Civil diſcord
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119648:7"/>is moſt deſtructive to Piety, Virtue, Learning, and Commerce; But, could we once more ſettle upon our true <hi>Engliſh</hi> bottome, we ſhould then be young and luſty as the <hi>Eagle,</hi> our ruſt would ſoon look bright, our age renew, our bloud ſpring, our ſpirits revive; And as if there were a return of our Golden age, <hi>every one might, once more, ſit ſecurely under his own Vine;</hi> There might then again <hi>be Peace within our Wals, and Plenty in our Palaces; No leading into Captivity; No complaining in our ſtreets; The bleſſed condition of that City which is at unity in it ſelf, of that People, which hath the Lord for their God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Common Intereſt invites you Magiſtrates to be very ſtrict and induſtrious; Subjects, in their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Capacities, active to promote, however diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creetly paſſive, and cordially willing to embrace ſuch wholeſome Lawes, as are likelieſt to eſtabliſh Juſtice, and ſecure Property. To delight in broyles, is proper only for ſuch, as either may hope to gain, but cannot fear to looſe; or ſuch as have enriched themſelves by Fraud, or Rapine, and being now poſſeſt of <hi>Naboths</hi> Vineyard, imagine (perhaps not without cauſe) that our unſettlement is their beſt Protection: But you, whom I ſuppoſe in effect, to divide the legall Intereſt of your Countrey, the Lands juſtly deſcending, or fairly purchaſed, the Goods duely gotten, betwixt you, are certainly obliged to avoid Faction, as you would do Plunder or Sequeſtration; to endeavour a ſober accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of differences (if any ſhould happen) as the title <hi>Paramount,</hi> by which you muſt hold your Eſtates.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:119648:7"/>
            <p>Common danger, and neceſſity at once threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens, and admoniſhes you to joyne your <hi>Counſels</hi> and <hi>Forces</hi> for mutuall preſervation, as good <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riners</hi> and honeſt <hi>paſſengers</hi> effectually do, when the Veſſel wherein they are altogether embarqued, is either diſtreſt with a <hi>Storm,</hi> or aſſaulted by <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates.</hi> I have no deſign to aggravate your juſt fears and reall dangers, which doubtleſſe are many and great, and to moſt of you (I preſume) viſible, onely let me beg of you to uſe your talent of Reaſon; to conſult with <hi>the pillow of your Experience,</hi> to recol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect your fragments of <hi>Hiſtory:</hi> which will all ſhew you your Condition, as in a faithfull Mirrour. And may I hope convince you; That God hath now ſet <hi>plenty</hi> and <hi>famine, Liberty</hi> and <hi>Thraldome, Life</hi> and <hi>Death</hi> before you, thoſe the <hi>guerdons</hi> of your Moderation, and Obedience, theſe the inevitable <hi>Conſequences</hi> of froward and peremptory diſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: That as on your right hand, you have a <hi>Land</hi> of <hi>promiſe,</hi> the <hi>throne</hi> of <hi>David,</hi> the <hi>pomp</hi> and <hi>great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> of <hi>Solomon,</hi> Or, (to go no further for inſtance, then our <hi>own ſtage,</hi>) the bleſſings which from the <hi>Coronation of Queen Elizabeth,</hi> to the late <hi>unhappy Warre,</hi> this Nation, (unthankfuly I fear) enjoyed. whilſt all her <hi>Neighbours</hi> envied, ſo on your left ſtands a vaſt Wilderneſſe, The defection of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roboam,</hi> The Uſurpations of <hi>Samaria,</hi> the ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the <hi>Gracchi,</hi> the <hi>Conſpiracie</hi> of <hi>Catiline,</hi> the Proſcriptions of <hi>Scilla,</hi> the Oligarchy of <hi>Athens,</hi> and perhaps at laſt, <hi>Monarchy</hi> with a <hi>vengeance,</hi> in the perſon of <hi>Caligula,</hi> or <hi>Nero; Rump</hi> and <hi>Bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bones, Levellers</hi> and <hi>Saints rampant, Jack ſtraw,</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:119648:8"/>and <hi>Watt Tylar, Knipperdoling</hi> and <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Ley<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> are at your elbowes, make your election at your <hi>perill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The difficulty, or rather (I hope) impoſſibillity for any ſingle party (as a Party) to gain, much more to hold the power of dictating to the <hi>Nation,</hi> ſhould diſpoſe you to the ſtudy of <hi>Univerſall inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts,</hi> (our preſent <hi>Elyxir</hi>) to an enquiry for ſuch Expedients and temperaments in Policy as in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, are only ſafe, or durable, and ſurely after long hoſtility moſt ſeaſonable. The baits of faction are now God be thanked all grown ſtale, The net is now vainly ſpread in the ſight of the Bird; <hi>Rooks</hi> and <hi>Daws</hi> have both learned to ſmell Gunpowder at a reaſonable diſtance, The <hi>Foxe</hi> of ſanctyfied impoſture hath been hunted out of all his retreats. And the fury of uſurpation purſued, as it were from bogge to bogge; The fiend hath appeared in all his guiſes and hath not a <hi>Vizour</hi> left which we are not acquainted with. Neither is there (one would think) fuell for a new flame, either in our Spirirs or Purſes; Thoſe being with long ſickneſſe, and much wearineſs compoſed and framed I truſt to <hi>Sobriety</hi> and <hi>Caution,</hi> Theſe ſo exhauſted, that we are ſcarce able to pay our <hi>preſent Taxes;</hi> We have, <hi>(God knows)</hi> little plate left to carry to <hi>Guild-Hall,</hi> we cannot ſpare another fifth and twentieth part, <hi>Vaſt loans,</hi> or <hi>Benevolencies,</hi> And <hi>fifty Subſidyes at once; Publique Faith</hi> will furniſh a Faction but with ſlender ſumms, its credit being much diſpara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, by what is paſt and more ſuſpected for the future, ſo as there is little danger unleſs meer wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſs
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119648:8"/>ſhould again make us to ſwagger, or our Monies burning (as we ſpeak <hi>proverbially</hi>) in our pockets, for want of other vent, ſend us to buy <hi>ſaddles, Buff-Coats,</hi> and <hi>gaudy Feathers,</hi> &amp;c. who, I take it, have, by this time, diſcovered, that there is more uſe of bread, then Ammunition, of cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, then harneſſe. Fears and jealouſies muſt be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al ones, if they much alarm us; It muſt appear to be indeed Gods own cauſe, before we ſhall again ſtir to propagate, or perhaps defend it, The Oath of a <hi>Tribune</hi> or word of a <hi>Vicar</hi> wil not be taken in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the <hi>higheſt Concernment,</hi> either ſpirituall or civill, If the <hi>Preacher</hi> ſummon us to our Tents we ſhall be apt to enquire <hi>Quo warranto;</hi> How he came by his Trumpet, whether he found his Doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine in his text, or coyned it in his fancy; Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Scripture</hi> and <hi>Antiquity:</hi> Or ſome very <hi>ino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern Father,</hi> (I will not ſay, <hi>Pamphleteere</hi>) furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed him with his <hi>Arguments</hi> and <hi>proofs;</hi> Let it, I pray be added, that even our <hi>Confuſion</hi> may in this particnlar turn to our <hi>Advantage:</hi> For being di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted as we are with ſuch a Variety of <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> and <hi>Intereſts</hi> which can never agree, but in the <hi>Negative,</hi> and will certainly all joine againſt any engroſſer of <hi>Dominion,</hi> that party which ſhall ſo uſurp, will ſtand as a Butt, to empty the Quiver, A meer <hi>Iſhmaell</hi> defying, and defyed by all men.</p>
            <p>The eaſineſs of obtaining quiet, ſhould encourage you to ſeek a little for that Jewel, which (me-thinks) you cannot chooſe bnt find, it lies ſo plainly in your view, God I know theauthor of al peace, is chiefly to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:119648:9"/>be conſulted and invoked by Prayer, that he would open our eys, encline our hearts, and bleſſe ourende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, but then we muſt come with ſincere minds and not as St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> moſt ingeniouſly confeſſes of himſelf that he prayed indeed devoutly againſt his <hi>Luſts,</hi> but withall, ſecretly wiſhed that God would not hear him; The truth is, our peace is not farre off, if we do not thruſt it from us, it is nigh at hand, nay it is within us <hi>Self deniall, Integrity</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a <hi>worldly Byaſſe,</hi> the Chriſtian duties of forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, and bearing with, each others infirmity, <hi>Wari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> in <hi>affirming, Charity</hi> in <hi>judging, Modeſty</hi> in <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding, Meekneſſe</hi> in <hi>receding,</hi> theſe are our ſure and certain guides in the way to <hi>Settlement;</hi> Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry faction would have <hi>Peace</hi> its own way, All pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe to welcome it. But few that I hear, will meet it; For whatſoever they find to be moſt profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble or honourable or ſecure for themſelves, that they are apt to propound, as effectuall, and <hi>Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall</hi> to our <hi>Peace;</hi> Not to inſtance too parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly, ſure I am, that the being of the <hi>Church,</hi> and well being of the <hi>Nation</hi> doth not conſiſt in all thoſe appurtenances, which ſome would obtrude, as neceſſary; Many of them, perhaps, are very <hi>commendable</hi> and <hi>expedient,</hi> if they may be procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red without evident hazard of incurring miſchiefs, farre more conſiderable for the preſent, then their convenience; For gold may be dear bought, And that <hi>Vniformity</hi> will coſt too much, which is pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed with loſſe or danger of <hi>Vnity:</hi> When a ſure foundation is firſt layd, It will then be time to build magnificently, and to contrive not only for
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:119648:9"/>meer uſe, but <hi>Ornament</hi> and <hi>Accommodation.</hi> Till then all ſides ſhould learn to content themſelves, with that which may, or rather, muſt be, and not vainly expect that which never can be or at leaſt cannot now; Wherein much experience and ſome deſcretion would adviſe them, not to hunt too ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerly, or queſt too loud upon every ſcent, ſince yielding may prevail where ſtubborneſſe never ſhal: Were this <hi>Principle</hi> and <hi>Spirit</hi> infuſed into our <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triots,</hi> it were already a fair and hopefull <hi>progreſſe</hi> in their great work, for the differences which for the moſt part appear to be more in the <hi>skirts</hi> then <hi>hody</hi> of our <hi>Religion</hi> or <hi>Government,</hi> would moſt of them be ſoon accorded, and the reſt vaniſh of themſelves; Or if any ſhould yet remain, the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> of a <hi>Parliament</hi> duely conſtituted, is a <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicature</hi> in this <hi>Nation,</hi> without <hi>exception</hi> or <hi>appeal</hi> worthy to command, if not our <hi>Active,</hi> yet at leaſt our <hi>Paſsive Obedience;</hi> A <hi>Guardian,</hi> in whoſe cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtody, I am ſure our <hi>Liberties,</hi> and I hope, our <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences</hi> are very ſafe.</p>
            <p>The <hi>zeal</hi> of your <hi>Religion</hi> ſhould provoke you to beſtir your ſelves, in a time of great need, and quit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting your <hi>punctilo</hi>'s, to intend the main; You all alike profeſſe to be ſincere <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and ſome of you <hi>Zealots</hi> to a kind of tranſportation, ſo as to ſcorne Peace, where you think truth is, unleſs both conſiſt, concerned more eſpecially, tender you have alwaies been in your bowels, large in your <hi>bounty,</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulous in your <hi>Correſpondence,</hi> forward in your <hi>Aſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance</hi> towards the <hi>Evangelicall Churches</hi> in foraign parts, when oppreſſed, or but threatned with any <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution;</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:119648:10"/>Upon this account, our late <hi>Princes</hi> have, at the requeſts of their <hi>Parliaments</hi> and people free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and frequently engaged themſelves both in <hi>Wars,</hi> and <hi>Treaties,</hi> ſometimes eſpouſing their <hi>Quarrell,</hi> ſometimes compromiſing it for them, eſpecially the <hi>French Proteſtants,</hi> on whoſe behalf our <hi>Kings</hi> have long ſtood both as <hi>Champions</hi> of <hi>their Liberty,</hi> and ſureties for their good behaviour; And indeed without our interpoſing, they muſt needs have been long ſince ſwallowed up by their mighty Foes; Their adverſary, beſides the inequality of Forces, having this great advantage, that he was their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted <hi>Soveraign;</hi> You cannot but hear what <hi>Monſtrous Counſells</hi> are now hatching at <hi>Rome,</hi> what ominous beginnings there are in <hi>France,</hi> all grounded upon this preſumption, That <hi>England</hi> hath other fiſh to fry; And that the work may be diſpatched before we are at leaſure to look abroad; Our <hi>Phanaticks,</hi> they, I think, are, a gagge in our mouthes, a <hi>Remora,</hi> to our <hi>Carreere,</hi> (I wiſh we find no other Obſtructions,) were we once ſetled, <hi>Rome</hi> would ſoon deſiſt, and <hi>France</hi> perhaps be made re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent; But whilſt our diviſions continue, we muſt not hope to maintain our outworks, nor I fear, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend our Walls, againſt enemies ſo powerfull, and lately ſo united by their General peace which, in all probability, may ſoon ferment into a <hi>Catholique</hi> League.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Your common duty, above all, obliges you, (And that, <hi>not for Wrath, but Conſcience, ſake</hi>) if you muſt contend, That it be not for <hi>Dominion,</hi> but <hi>Loyalty,</hi> not with <hi>ſtrife,</hi> but <hi>honeſt emalation</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:119648:10"/>You of the <hi>Cavalier</hi> Party (who pretend to a kind of <hi>Primogeniture</hi>) ſhew now, that you are true, not only to the <hi>Perſon</hi> and <hi>Authority,</hi> but to the <hi>Intereſt</hi> of your <hi>Maſter,</hi> for which you are ready (if need be) to <hi>ſacrifice</hi> your own: That you are <hi>Royalliſts</hi> not for <hi>Faction,</hi> but <hi>pure Allegiance,</hi> and could be content to follow thoſe Enſignes, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſuch conſiderations, as ſway only with <hi>Merce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries:</hi> That your <hi>bleeding Countrey</hi> hath ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in you, as well as your <hi>baniſhed Prince,</hi> and that your <hi>Loyalty</hi> hath not <hi>devoured</hi> your <hi>Charity; Confute,</hi> in Gods name, their <hi>Calumnies,</hi> who dayly repreſent you, as Perſons, whom nothing can pleaſe, but meer <hi>Tyranny,</hi> to have a <hi>Grand-Seignour</hi> for your Prince, you his <hi>Janiſſaries;</hi> The <hi>Nation,</hi> at his <hi>mercy,</hi> and your <hi>feet;</hi> Men ſo contracted in your <hi>principles,</hi> and fettered with <hi>Jure Divino</hi>'s, that no <hi>Jus humanum</hi> may be admitted, or once mentioned. You <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> who (by the voice of the people, in moſt Counties declining you) may perceive, That virtue is gone out of you; and that you ſuffer not a little in your Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, upon former accounts; If your own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences ſhall (as perhaps they may) ſecond here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the votes of your Countrey-men; Now that it is in your power not only to make amends, but me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, Pay all your arrears of Virtue and Loyalty, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with thoſe vows of Truth, Juſtice, and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty which I am confident you have often made in your late Extremities; Wipe of all thoſe ſtaines at once, that for the preſent may ſeem to blemiſh thoſe virtues, which in many of you are very Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:119648:11"/>and would ſhine bright, if theſe Cloudes were once diſpelled; Your aftergame is very good. The Law is now in your hands, and to you muſt be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged the chief honour of relieving your <hi>Country</hi> in its great diſtreſſe, when alas, a <hi>Royalliſt</hi> could not hold up his hand, except it were at the Barre; Proceed, therefore generouſly and undaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly in the performance of your own Duties, and maintenance of our Liberties, Be ſtill good <hi>Subjects,</hi> and good <hi>Citizens, Chriſtians,</hi> and <hi>Engliſhmen,</hi> let your ſtoutneſſe marry your Allegiance, and your Intereſt be ſubordinate to them both; Above all, let your moderation appear to all men, and be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident, that in ſo doing, your <hi>Countrey</hi> will bail you, and the Nation will be concerned not only in Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude but real Sympathy, that not any of thoſe dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers which the <hi>Phanaticks</hi> ſuggeſt, ſhall befall you, nor a hair of your head periſh.</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:119648:11"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
